<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A salutation to the church of God the spouse of Christ coming out of the wilderness leaning upon her beloved And more particularly to the young and tender members of her body. By one who travels in spirit for the preservation of peace and love, and unity among the children of God, William Loddington.</title>
            <author>Loddington, William, 1626?-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48938</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2806</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216896</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828611</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828611</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33042</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48938)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33042)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1915:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A salutation to the church of God the spouse of Christ coming out of the wilderness leaning upon her beloved And more particularly to the young and tender members of her body. By one who travels in spirit for the preservation of peace and love, and unity among the children of God, William Loddington.</title>
                  <author>Loddington, William, 1626?-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Cooke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXII. [1682]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christianity --  Essence, genius, nature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian union --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33042:1"/>
            <p>A SALUTATION TO THE CHURCH OF GOD The <hi>Spouſe</hi> of CHRIST Coming out of the Wilderneſs leaning upon Her BELOVED.</p>
            <p>And more particularly to the Young and Tender Members of Her Body.</p>
            <p>By one who travels in Spirit for the Preſervation of Peace and Love, and Unity among the Children of God, <hi>William Loddington.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Cooke,</hi> MDCLXXXII.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33042:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33042:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:33042:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33042:3"/>
            <head>A Salutation to the Church of God, the Spouſe of Chriſt coming out of the Wilderneſs, leaning upon Her Beloved.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Righteous Houſhold of God, built upon the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf being the chief Corner ſtone! The Lord thy God which hath gathered thee from the barren Mountains, and fitly framed thee into an holy Building, hath in free Love and mercy been pleaſed, (Bleſſed be his name) to let me ſee in my latter dayes, a glimps of thy, Beauty, and to taſt of thy Heavenly bread and living Water, ſealed up from impure Hearts, and incloſed as a Garden from the wild Beaſts of the Forreſts.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THis Morning being the 4 of the 2 Mo. in the year 1682. even by break of day, The ſence of my Mercies, and thy Sorrows and Exerciſes, <hi>O Woman cloathed with the Sun,</hi> came ſo powerfully within me,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33042:4"/>that they kindled a Deſire to ſalute thee, and thy tender Children on this wiſe, before I put off this my Earthly Tabernacle which in courſe of nature cannot be long.</p>
            <p>But as I write, an inward kind of ſhame and dejectedneſs ariſes from the thought of my former unkindneſs to thee, and would as it were cloud the Light, and ſtop my Spirit, from this manifeſtation of my Love. Not that I ever openly perſecuted thee in railing Words or violent Actions; No I may rather ſay, I was, as many now are, among the Number of thy more ſubtil and dangerous oppoſers, who under pretence of <hi>Goſpel</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, Chriſts Commands, and Scripture Examples, do the more hurt, and grieve thy Spirit more than a profane Enemy. I verily thought in my young Zeal for God thirty years ago, that I might have done ſome things againſt thee: for I feared then, thy chief and <hi>Principal</hi> Members, were De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers, I could not reliſh their Doctrine of beating ſwords into Plow ſhares, and Pikes into pruning Hooks, in that day. But I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained mercy, becauſe I diſputed and argued Ignorantly againſt thee, being covered with that vail, which is this day over the Hearts of many in reading the Writings of Chriſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33042:4"/>and his Apoſtles, as it was over the Hearts of many of old in reading <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</p>
            <p>But the Lord thy God, glory to his name, hath rent much of the vail, and in mercy given mea ſence of another kind of war-fare and other Weapons, which would the Beaſt-like Nature, and carnal <hi>Spirit</hi> incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably. Now I feel thy Wiſdom, and my own Weakneſs, thy Wiſdom, or rather the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom given thee from aboye is firſt pure, and can by no means defend or contend for any unjuſt or unholy thing, for profit, Honour, or affections ſake. It is alſo peacable, loving and kind, even to its Enemies: not rendring <hi>Evil,</hi> for <hi>Evil;</hi> but Bleſſing for railings. O little flock! Thou art eaſy to be entreated. Some of thy own profeſſed <hi>Friends</hi> know it to be true. How tender have I ſeen thee, in admoniſhing, intreating and reproving, when an airy, conceited, unruly Spirit, has entred them. O thou beloved of the Lord! Thou art beautiful within: And thy order is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, wrought by the heavenly Wiſdom, and not of Fragments and ſhreads of mans Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:33042:5"/>
            <p>How do thy envious and ſubtile Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries fret and chafe to ſee thee travelling in good order, even as an Army with Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: Yea, there is a fear ſeizeth them to ſee thee walk wiſely, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.15. Hence ariſe ſo many endeavours ſo many deviſes to diſorder thy Camp, and ſo to weaken thy Hands in thy <hi>Spiritual Warfare.</hi> Sometimes profane high Spirits aſſault and carry away thy outward <hi>Subſtance,</hi> abuſe thy Friends and Impriſon them often unto Death. But when this roaring Lyon ſees he cannot hurt thee, then he craftily transforms himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Angel of Light. And here I feel my Heart and Life concern'd for thy young and tender Babes, whoſe years in this World, as well as in Truth, have been but few. Theſe are in greater danger than thoſe of full Age, who by reaſon of uſe, have their ſences ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed to diſcern both good and evil, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.14. Theſe are ſooneſt allured with fine <hi>Words,</hi> eſpecially when ſpoken by ſuch as call themſelves the <hi>Chriſtian Friends,</hi> and can be as bold as <hi>Hannaniah, Jer.</hi> 28.3. ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God of Iſrael,</hi> when he ſaies no ſuch matter, and under pretence of breaking the Yoke of <hi>Babilon,</hi> in a heat endeavour to break off the Yoke of Chriſt thy Husband.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:33042:5"/>
            <p>Dear young Sons and Daughters of New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> now coming down from God out of Heaven, having no need of Sun or Moon, for the <hi>Lord God</hi> is the <hi>Light</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; keep to this <hi>Light</hi> and it will keep you within the walls of this holy City. I know there is a deceitful voice abroad, calling you out, while it bids you look within, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Liberty, it ſelf being a Servant of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption; crying out againſt you Elder Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Siſters ſometimes as <hi>Babel Builders,</hi> it ſelf being in my underſtanding but a <hi>Painted Virgin Daughter of Babilon,</hi> Iſa. 47.1. And ſometimes as Apoſtates, while it ſelf is intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing an Apoſtacy from the firſt Principles of <hi>Truth,</hi> ſeeking to limit the holy one of <hi>Iſrael</hi> under colour of keeping to that which firſt convinced you. It may not be unſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to tell you my own experiences of <hi>Gods</hi> Love in this very particular. I had fell into the Snare, if the Lord had not ſtay'd me. Let high <hi>Spirits</hi> eſteem it a reproach to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge any weakneſs; <hi>There is great peace in doing it,</hi> Pſal. 32.3. (Provided it be not done for any fear or favour of Man) but in a true ſence of mercy in the deliverance.</p>
            <p>When I firſt heard Some among us, of no mean gifts as I thought, and for whom I had
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33042:6"/>more than common affection, cry out againſt <hi>Impoſitions, Innovations,</hi> and formalities I confeſs it made a great impreſſion upon me, having an old fixed <hi>Zeal</hi> in me againſt all Perſecution for <hi>Conſcience ſake.</hi> So the <hi>Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies againſt Forms,</hi> (<hi>Perſecution</hi> generally ſpringing from dead <hi>Forms</hi>) was ſo taking and pleaſant, that I did not in the leaſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt, any ſuch <hi>Snake</hi> as <hi>Anarchy</hi> lay hid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe <hi>flowers</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> wherefore in true <hi>affection</hi> to a true <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> I writ to ſome <hi>Friends,</hi> among whom I obſerved ſome things, that I miſtruſted had a tendency to <hi>Impoſition,</hi> and I worded it high with them to prevent all Appearances of that Evil. And though I can truly ſay this was the utmoſt of my Intention, yet ſome began to fear I was running into <hi>Separation</hi> and <hi>Confuſion.</hi> But I was in peace miſtruſting <hi>Nothing,</hi> till I felt a wrong <hi>Spirit</hi> catching at it, and about to make a further uſe of it, yea and applying in Print (unknown to me) ſome things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Friends,</hi> which I had writ againſt <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> then I began to doubt ſome wrong thing was at work in me alſo, and that I was not well informed.</p>
            <p>And then I began more narrowly to mind and obſerve the <hi>Spirits</hi> on both ſides, and in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33042:6"/>the <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Meaſure</hi> of <hi>Gods Wiſdom</hi> given to me, to ſearch to the Root of the Matter (laying aſide perſonal charges and diſcharges) and was ſatisfied. So the Lord will by degrees enlighten and ſatisfie all whoſe hearts in Simplicity are ſingly bent to honour him, and will keep them from wandering either to the <hi>right hand or the left.</hi> The <hi>left hand</hi> Tryalls <hi>viz. Perſecutions</hi> of open <hi>Enemies,</hi> to bring you back to weak diſanull'd <hi>Forms</hi> and <hi>Elements,</hi> I do not much fear. The right hand Snares take moſt. Theſe are laid by ſuch as pretend to be in the right way, for <hi>God,</hi> for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for <hi>Scripture,</hi> yea for the <hi>Doctrin of our Day, The Light within.</hi> And here the <hi>Enemy</hi> of your <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> has crept in, under a ſpecious pretence againſt <hi>Forms, Orders</hi> and <hi>Impoſitions</hi> to divide and lay waſt, by oppoſing good <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> But dear <hi>Friends,</hi> know there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any gathering of <hi>People</hi> though into the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> but they had alſo a form or Order, though many have had the form without the <hi>Power.</hi> It's true, the form to the <hi>Power</hi> may be valued but as the ſhell to the <hi>Kernell:</hi> Yet we know the ſhell is ſervicable in its place, and therefore not to be neglected or ſpoiled. The leaves of the tree of life have a ſervice, though not ſo much as the fruit.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:33042:7"/>
            <p>Stand faſt therefore in the living <hi>Power</hi> and form of <hi>Godlineſs</hi> which you are already convinced of. And if any thing as yet be hid from you, the <hi>Lord</hi> in due time will reveal it, if you keep <hi>Faithful, quiet, meek,</hi> and tender under your own. Do nothing in bare <hi>Imitation,</hi> I know it will hardly ſtand a <hi>Tryal</hi> for a little profit, much leſs a <hi>Fiery Tryal.</hi> Wait to feel a real ſervice for God in what you do. There is no inſignificant needleſs things in the houſe of God; though ſome things may ſeem to be ſo at the firſt <hi>Veiw</hi> to many as they did to me.</p>
            <p>Hence ariſes the great cry againſt <hi>Innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> that is, making new orders, forms, and changes. But though the deſign in this Cry is to reproach Truth: Yet <hi>Wiſdom</hi> ever was and will be juſtified of her <hi>Children.</hi> They know that the Spirit of the Lord may now as well as formerly make <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> ſuitable to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Occaſions</hi> and <hi>Services</hi> of <hi>Truth.</hi> And <hi>Submiſion</hi> to theſe things, cannot properly be called <hi>Submiſions</hi> to men (there lies the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon miſtake) but to the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> in them. And this is <hi>Chriſts Spiritual Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> or <hi>Government</hi> by his Spirit over the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of his People. Here is no ruling by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33042:7"/>
               <hi>force</hi> and <hi>violence,</hi> but by an inward power and <hi>Authority</hi> which the <hi>Lord</hi> gives to ſome according to his own <hi>Will,</hi> as it is written, ſome to be <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> ſome <hi>Prophets,</hi> ſome <hi>Teachers,</hi> ſome helps and <hi>Governments,</hi> (<hi>Helpers</hi> in <hi>Governing</hi>) and all for edifying the <hi>Body of Chriſt,</hi> Eph. 4.12. 1 Cor. 12. Were this <hi>Government</hi> well underſtood, all would be contented in their <hi>Places</hi> the Lord hath ſet them, in all whiſperings and evil ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſings would ceaſe. There would be an univerſal bearing one anothers <hi>Burdens,</hi> and ſo <hi>fulfilling the Law of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Little Children it ariſes in me to remind you of what is written 1 <hi>John.</hi> 2.19. That ſuch as go from us, are not off us, for if they had been of us, they would no doubt have continued with us. I can never believe ſuch have a right <hi>Spirit</hi> renewed within them, that prefer not <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> above their chief Joy <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.6. If they had had but any true ſence of the publique Scandals of open <hi>Enemies</hi> of the <hi>private mournings</hi> and <hi>heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breaking Sorrows</hi> of their dear tender <hi>Friends,</hi> of the ſtumbling Block in the way of <hi>Friends, ſober inquiring People,</hi> all which certainly follows and fallsheavv upon Seperation, they durſt never have acted and <hi>Printed</hi> what I
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33042:8"/>have read. Away with all Pretenders to Truth, that are not tender of its Honor.</p>
            <p>But what is the Subſtance (if any of you ſhould inquire) of all theſe <hi>Ont-cries</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints?</hi> In ſhort, men are exalted and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are exalted. In true Love I deſire every ſuch <hi>Complainers</hi> to ſearch narrowly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelf to ſee if there be nothing in him that thinks it ſelf not high enough eſteemed, and therefore pecks at others. Surely no <hi>Profeſſor</hi> of our bleſſed ſelf denying Principle dare like <hi>Heroſtrotus,</hi> fire a <hi>Temple</hi> to get a <hi>Name.</hi> Yet formerly I as little thought ſuch as threw down <hi>Lordly power,</hi> would have made themſelves <hi>Lords,</hi> as ſome now will be men of War, who in <hi>deriſion</hi> call others <hi>G. F</hi>'s men of War. But how are men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men exalted? By meeting apart: By having <hi>General Meetings,</hi> to look to the well ordering of things among particular Meetings; What hurt can be in all this. As to the firſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider which Women are moſt exalted, and as it were eclipſe the Head-ſhip of the man; Whether thoſe that deſire to ſit, and are tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en in to ſit in equal power and freedom to ſpeak and act, <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con,</hi> among the men in all Buſineſſes; Or thoſe Women, who meet by themſelves, ordering all matters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33042:8"/>themſelves, ſuitable and proper for them, according to the Wiſdom of <hi>God</hi> giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to them, and all in <hi>Submiſion</hi> to and with the conſent and unity of the mens <hi>Meetings.</hi> Methinks this very <hi>Conſideration</hi> is enough to ſatisfie any rational impartial Man. And as to the <hi>General Meeting,</hi> What Evil has it done? Nay have not <hi>Friends</hi> generally had great both <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal Advantages</hi> thereby <hi>Pure Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Scripture</hi> teach, that the more Counſel, the greater ſafety; even as the more <hi>Lights</hi> gathered together make the greater <hi>Light.</hi> I know no viſible thing not liable to corruption; but methinks they that diſliked this order, at firſt ſhould and would if they had been of a <hi>right Spirit</hi> have kept their place, and propoſed another more ſervicable to <hi>Truth,</hi> and leſs liable to be taint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and then no doubt others would have felt unity with them: But it plainly argues a <hi>Contentious Spirit</hi> to find fault with what it cannot mend.</p>
            <p>I know the matters pretended to be in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy,</hi> relating to <hi>Order,</hi> are but as <hi>mint</hi> and <hi>Cummin</hi> if compared to the great and weighty Concerns of <hi>Truth,</hi> which ought eſpecially to be done, yet the other not to be left undone.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:33042:9"/>
            <p>In <hi>Math.</hi> 23.23. <hi>Judgment, Mercy</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> are recorded for the weighty things of the <hi>law,</hi> Now put theſe to tryal. How can he ſay he is for <hi>Judgment</hi> that diſpiſes the <hi>Judgment</hi> of his <hi>Brethren aſſembled</hi> in the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to give it? How is he for mercy, that for a thing indifferent (according to his own Opinion) will <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice Truth</hi> it ſelf, and expoſe all its <hi>Friends</hi> to the rage of an Ignorant violent <hi>Enemy?</hi> What <hi>Faith</hi> is that which would live in a latitude to temporize with all; to have more names than the <hi>Fathers</hi> written upon its <hi>Fore-head? Pure Nature</hi> will not ſuffer any <hi>Vine</hi> to bring forth the <hi>Fruit</hi> or <hi>Leaf</hi> of a <hi>Bramble.</hi> O the great abuſe this day of that precious <hi>Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Liberty of Conſcience!</hi> How many of an evil <hi>Conſcience,</hi> will talk fluently for its <hi>Liberty?</hi> How many ſtrain it for advantage as if they would have it ſignifie, to be of any <hi>Religion,</hi> and therefore are fierce againſt any viſible Geſture or <hi>Form,</hi> that may diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh them from others, crying out, <hi>Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Formality, Ceremony, Human Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, mans Orders,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In tender <hi>Love</hi> I deſire ſome would but Conſider, how ſhort they fall of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Reaſon of men of more inferiour
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33042:9"/>Principles, than what they pretend to. Hear what the Author of <hi>A ſeaſonable Diſcourſe againſt Popery,</hi> ſaies, Printed by <hi>H. Broom,</hi> page 35. <hi>What converſation can there be with theſe men</hi> (ſpeaking of the Juſuits) <hi>who are under no obligations of Society, no Character of notice or diſtinction, who at the ſame time are Prieſts and Hectors, Caſuiſts and Artificers, Presbyters, Ana-baptiſts, Quakers,</hi> (and why not <hi>Epiſcopalians</hi> too) <hi>Theiſts, Atheiſts, and amidſt all theſe very good Catholicks. Let any ſober man,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>judge what kind of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion this is in it ſelf, and how fit to be encouraged and ſubmitted to.</hi>—</p>
            <p>Thus dear young Friends, you may ſee how this kind of liberty is condemned by rational men, as unfit for Society among them, much more among you. Lord God of purity, Peace and Heavenly Order pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve you, that we may all ſtrive together, and not aſſunder for the Faith and ſound form of the Goſpel, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.27.</p>
            <p>If now any of you ſhould deſire to know what I underſtand by that liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which many, and I among them, have ſo zealouſly contended and deeply ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for. Know in brief, That it is a Liberty for every man to try all things, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle exhorteh; yet not to be alwayes trying, and never ſatisfied; but when he has tryed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33042:10"/>all, then to hold faſt that which in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience he finds beſt, without being compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by any outward force or puniſhment to joyn or worſhip with any others. And ſo likewiſe, that every body, Society, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of People have the ſame freedom of their ſeveral religious worſhips and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes without perſecuting one another; all living in obedience to the <hi>Civil</hi> Laws, that is ſuch as tend to the welfare of outward Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns. And this is the true juſt <hi>liberty;</hi> and not a <hi>liberty</hi> for Members of the ſame Body or Society to differ from each other, in things which deſtroy their <hi>Character</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> among them. But ſeeing I am ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>liberty</hi> let me mind you of two things more. Firſt of a plea I often meet with, that there are good men and bad of all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And ſo by conſequence ſecretly inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating they are all alike: But I hope you eaſily perceive the Serpents Poli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y in argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus for all Religions, that it is to make Peoples Conſciences pliable to any Religion that may come uppermoſt, or rather indeed to be of no Religion, that ſo they may ſhun all ſufferings upon Religious Accounts.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of a Spirit which thinks to juſtify its liberty by quoting your ancient Friends, as <hi>Paul</hi> did the <hi>Athenian</hi> Poets for their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:33042:10"/>
            <p>But as the caſe is different, ſo I truſt the effect will be; for <hi>Paul</hi> quoted the Poets for a right end and prevailed with ſome: But theſe, how can they expect to turn you to that which the Author they quote yet living teſtifies is not the ſence of his words, nor the intent of his mind to have you turned unto. <hi>To put a wrong Interpretation upon any mans writings, is a very bad ſort of Impoſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hold faſt the profeſſion of your Faith and form of ſound words,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.13. which you have received in the faith and Love of Chriſt Jeſus; from which ſome turn away: Of whom are <hi>Phygellus</hi>'s that is, ſuch as ſhun the eye or overſight of their Brethren, and <hi>Hermogenes</hi>'s, that is, ſuch as are born of humane Wiſdom, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. Mark what a weighty ſignification is in theſe very names, left upon Record for the Churches.</p>
            <p>And as for the deceaſed Friends ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, one of them <hi>viz. Iſaac Pennington</hi> I had often conference with. I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times objected his own ſayings, yea and read <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem over face to face in great affection to vindicate ſuch a Liberty which I then verily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hought might conſiſt with Good order. But I muſt do him right, I never heard him
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33042:11"/>conſent or give any Countenance, but rather a kind of Indignation would ariſe againſt my ſence of his words, which was the ſame as ſome now put upon them. But their actions now make it manifeſt, they drive at another end then I intended. And I verely believe he felt my Innocency, as ſome others have done even in my oppoſing them: for he did not ceaſe coming to me when oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity ſerved, and when we met, and talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of theſe differences, his labour ſtill was, that I would lay aſide that Wiſdom and Reaſoning which run me upon thoſe expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>I well remember the very place, where once as we were walking and diſcourſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Diſſenters, I fell to pleading for a <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration</hi> and compliance with them upon this conſideration, that I looked upon them, and the others to be all as Schollars in Chriſts School; only ſome werein a higher and others in a lower Claſs or form. But this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon he could not reliſh, his very Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance changed at it; and to this purpoſe he anſwered, That the difference was far otherwiſe, and that there was a Spirit quite contrary to Truth ſubtily working under their pretences; but a tenderneſs and bowels
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33042:11"/>of love and compaſion was in him towards the innocent among them.</p>
            <p>And I ſay the Truth in Chriſt, I lie not, my conſcience bearing me witneſs (Glory to thy name O Lord) that I have great heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and inward ſorrow for my loving Friends ſtil under the like miſtake as I was, who yet ſee not the tendency of the dividing Spirits fine devices. And when I conſider what ſweet comfort and Spiritual Refreſhment we have had together in the ſervice of the Lord; O that life (not death <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.15.) may ſeize upon them, ſaith my ſoul: that they may walk in the footſteps of Chriſts little flock, and feed their Kids by his ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hards tents! For why ſhould ye be (O dear Friends) as thoſe that are vailed, turning aſide from the flocks of his Companions? Let all thy Children (O God of Peace and love) dayly more and more witneſs, how pleaſant it is for Brethren to dwell together in unity: And how fitly its compared to the precious Ointment upon <hi>Aarons</hi> head, that ran down to the very skirts of his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>viz.</hi> to every member of the body: And to the dew of <hi>Hermon,</hi> that deſcended to all the mountains of Sion, <hi>viz</hi> the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Chriſt, for there the Lord command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33042:12"/>(and doth command) the bleſſing, even Life for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133.</p>
            <p>So, tender hearted Friends, feel the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of my Life in this Salutation, Deſpiſe not my <hi>Spiritual youth,</hi> its freſh with unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed love (praiſes to the Lord) and I truſt will ever be ſo, for a Spiritual Unity, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which Truth will not grow. My earthly Tabernacle declines apace, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens to its center, but my love to Gods heavenly Building (bleſſed be his Name) by his power is enlarged; and my Spirit rejoyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in feeling a Remnant zealous for it, and unanimous in promoting it through all oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions.</p>
            <p>I have ſeen the fruit of <hi>Diſcord</hi> among other Gatherings, and what hurt the Spirit of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otrephes</hi> has done among them: keep upon your watch, little flock, hold up your hearts and ſtand in the unity of the heavenly life and <hi>Amaleck</hi> can never prevail. No Weapon formed againſt you ſhall proſper; And every thing that would be exalted over you, ſhall fall: But you that are willing and obedient, even you who in Gods holy Order, are equally willing to obey or to rule, to rule or to obey as he pleaſeth to diſpoſe of you,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33042:12"/>ſhall eat the good things of his heavenly Land.</p>
            <p>So with this I ſhall conclude deſiring you dear young Friends to beware of running too faſt; its a great and common temptation in youth. A ſtrong Confidence may ſpring from the heat of your affection and may preſs you on to many things, yea even to publique Teſtimony, beyond your true Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fure of Life. I have known and felt this to be true, and have deeply ſuffered for it. <hi>Peter</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Fell under ſuch a like Confidence, and was convinced, that it was a wrong zeal which made him ſay, <hi>Though all ſhould be offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet would not he,</hi> Math 26.33. But he would ſay ſo no more, when Chriſt tried him with a queſtion directly to that purpoſe, <hi>John.</hi> 21.15.</p>
            <p>But I can tell you by experience how you may know when any motion is beyond your Meaſure. You will certainly feel (as when your bodyes are ſtrain'd beyond their natural ſtrength) a weakneſs and flatneſs, or as it were, a damp, fear or fainting will fall upon your Spirits afterwards; eſpecially if by any Friend oppoſed: But the true Birth and life brings with it, an inward Evidence
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33042:13"/>of peace and acceptance with the Lord, and feeling the inward Recompence of reward (not expecting any thing from Man) is bold in ſpeaking or acting what it certainly knows to be juſt and true; and having ſo done, is bold and valiant under all oppoſition againſt it.</p>
            <p>So the God of love, keep you all faithful to your <hi>Meaſure,</hi> and diligent in your place; all performing your Duties to each other in true humility and tenderneſs according to Scripture: So ſhall the Mountain of the <hi>Lords</hi> houſe be eſtabliſhed over of all Mountains, (all Gatherings) and all Nations ſhall flow unto it, <hi>Iſay.</hi> 2.2.</p>
            <p>To thy Name, bleſſed powerful God of Glory, who haſt redeemed us from the Iron furnace, from the <hi>Law</hi> of ſin and Death, who art now purifying and gathering to thy ſelf a peculiar People to ſit together in heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly places in Chriſt Jeſus, be all the pure thanksgivings and holy praiſes returned for all thy mercies and ſavours for Evermore.</p>
            <p>One thing more ariſes, let not this come into the hands of ſuch whom you feel ſinn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wilfully after they have received the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33042:13"/>knowledge of Truth, who, like <hi>Sanballet</hi> and <hi>Tobias,</hi> not only ſcoff at Gods Building, but alſo do their utmoſt to hinder it. Theſe will turn again and rent both this and you. But of ſome in tenderneſs ſcrupling have compaſſion, making a difference. And if this ſhould happen to come to the Eyes of any of my old Friends and Brethren under former Diſpenſations (for whom I can tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and heartily ſay I have as much, yea ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more love then ever) who perhaps may look ſomewhat diſcontentedly upon it, as a fruit of <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from what we formerly believed were <hi>Gods Ordinances</hi> and <hi>Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> let me deſire them to conſider how they will anſwer an <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> man if he charge them with Apoſtacy from their Church, which they verily believe is eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon as plain Scripture proof, as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve theirs is. And let them further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, whether they themſelves are of the ſame Judgment in all things as they were trained up in.</p>
            <p>I have often feared, That the very thoughts of being upbraided with <hi>Wavering, Changing, Inſtability</hi> or the like, is a ſtrong Snare to hold many in Bondage under weak and unprofitable forms and Elements. I
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33042:14"/>wiſh it have no influence upon Some now ſtanding in oppoſition to <hi>better Things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I grant, that to be toſſed too and fro (as many were in former quick National Turns from Popery to Proteſtancy and back again to Popery) is ſhamefully childiſh: But to preſs forward, and come to clearer mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtations of Chriſt the Light, as the <hi>Lord</hi> brings them forth by his Power in every age, is every mans Duty: And if therein he walk faithfully according to his Meaſure, patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bearing his croſs, he ſhall receive the Crown of eternal Life. <hi>Finally, Brethren, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Things are True, whatſoever things are Doneſt, whatſoever things are Iuſt, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever things are Pure, whatſoever things are Lovly, whatſoever things are of Good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port; if there be any Vertue, if there be any Praiſe, think on theſe things.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. L.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33042:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
